<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bemsibom Toh</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Bemsibom Toh</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 16:10:18 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>about</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>Hi there, my name is Bemsibom, but most people call me Bemsi. I was born and raised in Cameroon, but have lived in a few different places, including Nigeria, Ghana, the UAE, France, Belgium, and now the UK.&#xA;My academic background is in probability theory - I completed a PhD in Mathematics at Heriot-Watt University in Edinburgh, and then was a postdoctoral resesarch scientist at the University of Cambridge for a couple of years.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A gentle intro to Airflow</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/techblog/sample/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 16:10:18 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/techblog/sample/</guid>
      <description>So this is what airflow does</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Valuing common values</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/values/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/values/</guid>
      <description>I was talking to a friend the other day when we stumbled upon something obvious, but which I had never thought about before. When people usually talk about relationships, business or otherwise, they often refer to the necessity for the parties involved to have shared values. But I think there is a meta-value that is often overlooked: that of valuing those shared values over the differences that are inevitable among any group of people.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perspective</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/perspective/</guid>
      <description>Sometime ago I wrote an article on “self-improvement”. In it I posited that there are extensions of minimalism to the realm of personal relationships that make a lot of sense in the abstract, but are difficult to implement because they require that we ask ourselves a number of difficult questions, and therefore necessitate a certain degree of moral courage.&#xA;It seems to me that all the major decisions in life are of the same nature – not only the ones about what (or who) to remove from our lives to make them more productive.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Self Improvement</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/self_improvement/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2017 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/self_improvement/</guid>
      <description>One of the most common metaphors used to describe life is that of a race, where the goal is to get as far as possible in the shortest possible time . Naturally, most people would want to (run, and) reach the end of their race in the best condition possible; that is why we, as human beings, have spent the better part of history wondering how to live the good life – and inventing the concept of self-improvement in the process.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Running life&#39;s race</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/run_your_race/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/run_your_race/</guid>
      <description>There are many metaphors used to describe life.&#xA;Sometimes, life is described as some giant construction process: in one’s youth, the priority is (or should be) on setting a solid foundation, while middle and old age are devoted to setting the superstructure and enjoying one’s work respectively. Other times, life is described as a journey, with birth as a starting point, death as an end. Of course with the occasional hero and villain.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What do you expect?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/what_do_you_expect/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/what_do_you_expect/</guid>
      <description>“What do you expect from those close to you?”&#xA;I was asked this question some time ago, and, interestingly, I could not think of any precise answer. My mind just went blank.&#xA;Not that this is an entirely rare occurrence; my mind goes blank a lot more than I&amp;rsquo;d care to admit, but this time I thought it would be interesting to scratch this itch, and think about the whole idea of expectations in general.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The anglophone crisis II</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/anglophone_crisis_two/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/anglophone_crisis_two/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago, I wrote an essay on some of my views on what is a growing (‘alarming’ may be the appropriate word soon) problem in Cameroon: the Anglophone problem. In that essay, I assumed that the average reader of this essay would be quite familiar with the nature of the problem, and then moved to comment on more peripheral issues.&#xA;However, in the days since then, I have found several reactions which have led me to write this follow up.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The anglophone crisis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/anglophone_crisis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/anglophone_crisis/</guid>
      <description>For the past several days I, like every other English-speaking Cameroonian, have followed with avid interest the developments of the various strikes that have been going on in the country, as well as the flurry of emotions and opinions that have accompanied them.&#xA;The issue at hand is the “Anglophone problem”, which is, the marginalisation of the Anglophones in the country.&#xA;A few people tried to deny the presence of any such problem.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Talkers of virtue</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/talkers_of_virtue/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2016 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/talkers_of_virtue/</guid>
      <description>There are some people in life who have distinguished themselves by the way they speak. They are (or at least claim to be) the visionaries, the big thinkers, the idealists, the utopians to whom we give the power to provide the ideological frameworks upon which we build our lives and societies. Examples of such people include politicians, religious officials, activists and even some writers. They talk about the way things are supposed to be; they are able to see beyond what is, and are able to paint a picture of what could be… they make us aspire to become better versions of ourselves.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What are you jealous of?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/jealous/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2016 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/jealous/</guid>
      <description>It is the pit in the stomach. The shrills that come over you when you see them. Sometimes it makes you angry, other times it just frustrates you. Whatever it is, jealousy is not the nicest of emotions to feel. Not only because of its moral implications, but also because of the nature of the feeling itself.&#xA;However, if thought about differently, jealousy can actually be quite helpful.&#xA;The key to harnessing the power of this emotion is to realize that we are not jealous of everything.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What we don&#39;t know</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/what_we_dont_know/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2016 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/what_we_dont_know/</guid>
      <description>The older I get, the more apparent it becomes to me that nobody, apart from the parties involved, can actually know all the facts in a given situation. To be really honest, this is one of those things I am actually wondering whether I knew all along, or whether it is just dawning on me, and if this is the case, why it is so. Even supposedly simple issues such as everyday fights between friends or coworkers seem to be so loaded with controversy and history that one wonders whether things have always been this way, or whether it is another product of the lifestyle of our day.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Give them opportunity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/opportunity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/opportunity/</guid>
      <description>I have had the opportunity to live in another African country for a while now, with a cohort of other Africans from about 16 different African countries. I have learned and observed a good number of things during this time, and I think I have learned quite a deal about what Africa needs.&#xA;For the past few months, I have been considerably impressed, and frightened at the same time. Impressed because of the levels of talent and ambition I see amongst my peers.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The days are long….</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/long_days/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2016 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/long_days/</guid>
      <description>There is a certain sense of rhythm and regularity to human existence that we all come to notice at some point in our lives. The beating of the heart, the breathing in our lungs and the blinking of our eyes are all examples of bodily functions that occur rhythmically, and which are peculiar to each one of us. On a larger scale, we observe similar patterns in nature: changing of seasons, sunrise and sunset… which all occur with a certain sense of regularity.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What do we deserve?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/deserve/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/deserve/</guid>
      <description>A common theme in many of the conversations I have had recently is the story of the prodigal son, in the Bible. A simplified version of the story is as follows: A man has two sons, one who is reprobate, and the other, who is upstanding. The reprobate son asks for his share of the inheritance from his father, goes away and squanders it in some far away land. When poverty and shame drive him to his senses, he returns home, and finds an overjoyed father who welcomes him with open hands.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The problem with smart people</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/smart_people/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2016 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/smart_people/</guid>
      <description>When I was younger it was cliché to say (or at least think) that smart people had issues. There were sayings such as “A students teach B students to work for C students”, or that some people were “be book smart, but not street smart”. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t hard to finally internalize the message, and accept that being smart, or at least book smart, wasn&amp;rsquo;t such a great thing after all.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equality is overrated</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/equality/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2016 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/equality/</guid>
      <description>Today there is a lot of talk about equality in relationships. The overall idea is that there should be an equitable distribution of load between the partners in a relationship.&#xA;This is an idea with plenty of merit. For many centuries women were thought of as lesser human beings. They couldn’t get an education, work, or even own property. Which was terribly wrong.&#xA;Now there is a strong emphasis on equality, but in many ways it is as destructive as the original myths.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Cameroon entrepreneur itself into a brighter future?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/entrepreneur/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2016 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/entrepreneur/</guid>
      <description>A friend of mine recently drew my attention to a writing competition with the above title as subject. For what it’s worth, the said competition was open only to undergraduate students; since I am unfortunate enough to no longer be an undergraduate, I was not eligible.&#xA;However, I think the question itself merits attention, especially because of recent trends. Because of corruption and many other ills, many people have lost all faith in governments (not only in Cameroon, but all over Africa).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Debates</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/debate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/debate/</guid>
      <description>Interesting things happen when people disagree. In the best of cases, they genuinely listen to each other, following one another’s thought processes, analyzing their differences and finally learning plenty of new things in the process. In the worst of cases, they end up angry and frustrated. However, whatever the outcome, arguing things out is a vital part of life – whether “smaller” issues in personal relationships, or broader issues in culture at large.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why do we write?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2015 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/writing/</guid>
      <description>Many writers feel angst in face of the blank page 1. No matter how much experience they have, or what kind of things they write, there is a feeling of inadequateness that accompanies the writing process. Many questions come to mind: Does what I have to say make sense? Is it relevant? Am I saying it right? Are my arguments coherent? However, the most common question, and probably the most devastating, is: Has somebody else not already said this?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The pursuit of happiness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/pursuit_happiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2015 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/pursuit_happiness/</guid>
      <description>I recently listened to a group of people describe their aspirations for life, and was particularly intrigued by how often people said they wanted to be “happy”. Because people generally tend to hope for things they feel they lack, it was only natural for me to assume that they felt they were not happy at the moment. But they really seemed like very happy people to me, and so I proceeded to ask them what their conception of happiness was, and why it was that they didn’t think they were happy at the moment.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Education in Africa</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/education_africa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/education_africa/</guid>
      <description>Everybody knows that there are problems with the school systems in many African countries. Few teachers, poor infrastructure and general poverty hinder many students impede many students from getting quality education in the various educational institutions across the continent, especially the public schools.&#xA;A few people have stepped forward to do something about this problem. They have built organizations aimed at providing high-quality education to young people in under-privileged communities across the continent.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The academic experience at AIMS</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/aims_review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/aims_review/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago, I defended a Master&amp;rsquo;s thesis in Mathematical Sciences at AIMS-Ghana. A few days later, I received a transcript of my academic records, from the same institution. There was something particular about receiving the transcript that made me think about how the entire academic year has been for me, what I liked, what I did not like or understand, and what my impressions are about the AIMS academic experience in general, now that I have been through it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advice and trouble II</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/advice_two/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2015 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/advice_two/</guid>
      <description>I recently wrote an essay in which I investigated the reason why people get in trouble for giving advice. I received some very interesting feedback from quite a few readers, who pointed out something I had not considered at the time I was thinking about the other topic, and which I thought would be interesting to think about.&#xA;It was about a set of four words very few people like to hear: “I told you so”.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The morality of intentions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/intentions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2015 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/intentions/</guid>
      <description>Our actions do not always line up with our intentions. I wonder how this simple fact shapes our opinions of ourselves, and others.&#xA;There is a biblical quote I often hear from people trying to justify a certain course of action gone wrong: “Man looks at the outward appearance, but God looks at the heart.” This is usually said in a bid to imply that their hearts were in the right place, and that, even if the people around them do not recognize that, at least God does, because He sees the intentions behind the misunderstood actions.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advice and trouble</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/advice/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2015 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/advice/</guid>
      <description>I recently realized how often people get into trouble for giving advice, and I think it is because most (probably all) advice is bad.&#xA;People usually seek advice when facing some life decision, or when they find themselves in trouble and need direction on how to proceed. Usually, what happens is the following: person A explains the details of a given situation person B, who, (hopefully) after some contemplation, offers possible directions on how to proceed, alongside the possible outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Africa and leadership II</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/africa_devt_two/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2015 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/africa_devt_two/</guid>
      <description>In the first part of this essay, I suggested that bad leadership may not be the root of all the evils Africa is facing. Of course there is a leadership problem from all accounts, but then, I posited that this leadership issue is not the root, but somewhat of a stem, an intermediary in the whole underdevelopment process. I then supported Fred Swaniker&amp;rsquo;s theory on the weakness of the institutions throughout the continent, given that it happens to explain away many of the social phenomena we observe in Africa.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Africa&#39;s and leadership - I</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/africa_devt_one/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2015 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/africa_devt_one/</guid>
      <description>It seems to me that every African knows that the continent has issues, and, were you to ask any one of them what problems their continent faces, the number one response would be “bad leadership”. If you had asked me the same question sometime ago, I would probably have given you the same answer. But for a while now, I have been thinking about the whole bad leadership thing quite seriously, and why the problem is so particular to Africa.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aging</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/essays/aging/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/essays/aging/</guid>
      <description>I was born into a world where people celebrate birthdays. The exact reason I wonder sometimes, but I guess most people do so because it&amp;rsquo;s kind of a milestone… a celebration of life, a rite of passage to old age?&#xA;Today, I think about age, and what it represents. For the most part, age comes with wisdom ; a certain perspective, ripeness, gravitas. A sense of grounding in reality. When we are young, everybody believes in us.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
